Vamshi Krushna Lakavath

vamshikrishna2324@gmail.com | (425) 459-0489 | Vamshi Krushna L | LinkedIn | GitHub

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Highly analytical and research-oriented data analyst with over 3 years of work experience who can process and derive actionable insights from massive datasets. Equipped with strong programming and analytical skills with experience in data mining, data management, statistical analysis, data visualization, and storytelling.

SKILLS

Programming Language: SQL, Python

Tools and Software: Tableau, PowerBI, Excel, MySQL Workbench, BigQuery, MongoDB, Data Studio, Tableau Prep Builder, Jupyter Notebook, Google Colab, Microsoft Office, Redshift, S3.

Specializations: Database Management, Data Mining, Data Collection, Data Cleaning, Data Processing, ETL Process, Statistical Data Analysis, Exploratory Data Analysis, Data Visualization, Dashboard, and Reporting.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Processing Analyst, Infrrd.ai, San Jose, CA

Mar 2022 - Dec 2022

- Processed unstructured data by leveraging Infrrd's Intelligent Document Processing tool.
- Cleaned, transformed, and preprocessed raw data with 100K plus records. Dealt with duplicate records & missing values and ensured data quality and integrity. Conducted EDA analysis, outliers removal, and feature selection.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams and provided them with data analytics insights.
- Performed statistical data analysis, investigated trends and patterns, and visualized KPIs.

Tools: SQL, Python, Tableau, IDP, Excel, PowerPoint, Spreadsheets

Credit Analyst, Andhra Pradesh Grameena Vikas Bank, Mahbubnagar, India

Jul 2019 - Nov 2019

- Analyzed customers' credit reports, Financial and transactional data, and determined their loan eligibility.
- Created and maintained insightful tableau dashboards that track various key loan metrics of customers.
- Renewed and enhanced credit limit to more than 100 customers using insights from analytics and charts.
- Increased branch advances by 10%, and reduced bad loans by 30% which improved our profits by 12%.
- Detected account anomalies & prevented frauds and AML by analyzing financial and transactional reports.

Tools: SQL, Tableau, Excel, PowerPoint

Assistant Manager-Analytics, Union Bank of India, Pune, India

Jul 2017 - Apr 2019

- Studied daily operations of a branch that has approx. \$12.6M in business and provided ad-hoc analysis.
- Managed a customer database consisting of more than 100k customers.
- Generated daily reports using SQL, analyzed reports and created KPIs on Tableau that improved profits.
- Worked on KYC, Non-performing assets (NPA), Fraud prevention, and Anti-money laundering (AML).
- Assisted in quarterly and annual branch audits and inspections.

Tools: SQL, Tableau, Excel, PowerPoint

EDUCATION

Master of Science, Data Analytics San Jose State University, San Jose, CA

Dec 2022

Bachelor of Technology, Electrical & Electronics Engineering Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University Sep 2014

PROJECT EXPERIENCE

Sentiment analysis on the US drug reviews

Jan 2022 - May 2022

- Conducted sentiment analysis on the United States Drugs Reviews and achieved an accuracy of 89%.
- Developed Naive Bayes, Logistic Regression, Random Forest, and Ensemble Techniques.
- NLTK has been used for tokenization, removing stop words, and stemming. Encoded data using TF-IDF.

Real-Time Hand Gesture Recognition

Jan 2022 - May 2022

- Built deep learning models such as LSTM, Bi-LSTM, and GRU to detect real-time hand gestures by locating 21 coordinates on the hand and attained 80% accuracy for the LSTM model.
- OpenCV, MediaPipe, Keras, NumPy, Pandas, hyperparameter tuning, and TensorFlow framework were used.

Analysis of Credits and Grants of International Development Association (IDA) in Tableau Aug 2021 - Dec 2021

- Analyzed and visualized Credits and Grants of the IDA data for the past 65 years using Tableau.
- Identified most popular projects, average loan processing time, and country/region-wise credit allocation.
- Observed a 96% decline in credit approval from its peak of 2000B in 2011 to a low of 80B in 2021.
- Plotted data insights using a variety of intelligible charts and maps. Created interactive Tableau dashboards.

The United States Housing Market Trend analysis using Big Data Analysis Aug 2021 - Dec 2021

- Investigated the housing market data to demonstrate the trends and fluctuations during the years 2016 to 2021.
- Observed a 52% growth and inverse trend between the average prices & average no. of listings of houses.
- Conducted correlation analysis between population growth and price per sq. ft. growth in cities.
- Computed monthly, quarterly, and yearly returns during the period. Compared prices before and after COVID-19.
- Visualized insights, and automated the ETL process. Used AWS Glue, Athena, S3, Redshift, and Tableau.

Machine Learning Technologies to Detect Fraudulent Credit Card Transactions

Aug 2021 - Dec 2021

- Built ANN, Random forest, Logistic regression, SVM, and decision tree models to detect fraudulent credit card transactions. Attained the highest accuracy of 99.8%, precision of 99.7%, and false positive rate of 0.1% for ANN.
- Followed CRISP-DM methodology. Designed WBS and PERT charts for project management.

Restaurant Customer Rating Database using BigQuery SQL

Jan 2021 - May 2021

- Developed a Recommender Database Management System for restaurants in Mexico for the customers to choose their preferred restaurant based on cuisine, affordability, ambiance, parking, wait time, and rating.
- Identified 80% of the time ratings and reviews are responsible for restaurant selection.
- Implemented DDL, DML, DCL, and TCL techniques to Create, Insert, Update, Alter, Select, and Delete the tables.
- The database has been tested and evaluated. Created views, stored procedures, and functions.
- Methods and tools used: Entity-Relationship Model, BigQuery SQL, Dataproc, Excel, Lucidchart, and Data Studio.

COVID-19 Vaccination Progress Analysis

Jan 2021 - May 2021

- A big data project on GCP to analyze real-time COVID-19 world vaccination data.
- Identified the most popular vaccines, most & least vaccinated countries, and calculated the trend of the fully vaccinated and partially vaccinated people.
- Implemented Views, stored procedures, and window functions of SQL on BigQuery for advanced analytics.
- Utilized GCP services such as BigQuery, Cloud Storage, Pub/Sub, Dataflow, and Cloud Functions.